Finding Aid for William Herbert Hobbs pamphlets and reprints, 1889-1951
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Herbert Hobbs pamphlets and reprints 1889-1951
Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.
[724] DA 2; H682; P186
Professor of Geology at the University of Michigan; reprints of articles on various geological topics including his research and exploration in Greenland.
1 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a variety of sources.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Herbert Hobbs served as a professor of geology and director of the geology laboratory at the University of Michigan from 1906 to 1934. Born in Worchester, Massachusetts on July 2, 1864, he received a Bachelor of Science degree from Worchester Polytechnical Institute in 1883. He completed both master's and doctoral degrees at Johns Hopkins University. Before coming to Michigan, he served as curator of the geology museum and professor of mineralogy, metallurgy, and petrology at the University of Wisconsin.
Widely known for scientific expeditions to Greenland and worldwide geological research, he was also politically active, serving as chairman of the Ann Arbor branch of the National Security League during World War I. Many land formations have been named after Hobbs by explorer friends, including a mountain, several glaciers, and a strip of coastline in Antarctica.
In 1921, he charted little-known islands held by Japan with the help of the Japanese navy, information which became valuable to the U.S. government during World War II. For his scholarly and personal contributions, France awarded him the Chevalier Legion Honor in 1924. While at the University of Michigan, Hobbs led expeditions to Greenland in 1926, 1927, and 1928 to research his theories on the influence of the Greenland ice cap on weather. During the 1928 expedition, Hobbs participated in the rescue of two men whose plane had been forced down in Greenland during a trans-Atlantic flight.
In 1950, Hobbs donated his collection of approximately 750 publications on polar expeditions to the University Library. Hobbs himself had written 15 books and many articles on geological and political issues. He died in Ann Arbor, MI on January 1, 1953, at the age of 88.
The Hobbs collections consists of pamphlets and reprints of articles on various geological topics including his research and exploration in Greenland.
Subjects:
Geology.; Glaciers.; Greenland.
- Pamphlets and Reprints.
  - 1889
    - Ueber die Verwachsung von Allanit (Orthit) und Epidot in Gesteinen. (Box 1)
  - 1891
    - On a New Occurrence of Olivine Diabase in Minnehaha County, South Dakota. Read before the Wisconsin Academy of Sciences, Arts, and Letters, December 30, 1891. (Box 1)
  - 1892
    - Notes on a Trip to the Lipari Islands. Read before the Wisconsin Academy of Sciences, Arts, and Letters, June 3, 1892. (Box 1)
  - 1893
    - On the Geological Structure of the Mount Washington Mass of the Taconic Range. (Box 1)
    - Phases in the Metomorphism of the Schists of Southern Berkshire. Read before the Geological Society, August, 16, 1892. (Box 1)
    - Ueber den Volcanit, ein Anorthoklas-Augit-Gesten von der chemischen Zusamensetzung der Dacite. (Box 1)
  - 1895
    - Die krystallisirten Mineralien aus dem "Galena Limestone" des sudlichen Wisconsin und des nordlichen Illinois. (Box 1)
  - 1899
    - The Diamond Field of the Great Lakes. (Box 1)
    - Note on the Crystallography of a Reduction Product of Terpene-3-in-one. (Box 1)
    - A Spiral Fulgurite from Wisconsin. (Box 1)
  - 1900
    - The Problem of National Defense. (Box 1)
    - Suggestions Regarding the Classification of the Igneous Rock. (Box 1)
  - 1901
    - The River System of Connecticut. (Box 1)
  - 1902
    - The American Ancestry and the Descendants of William Herbert and Sara Kimball Hobbs. (Box 1)
    - Former Extent of the Newark System. (Box 1)
    - The Mapping of the Crystalline Schists. (Box 1)
    - The Old Tungsten Mine at Trumbull, Conn. (Box 1)
  - 1903
    - The Geological Structure of the Southwestern New England Region. (Box 1)
    - Meteorite From Algoma, Wisconsin. (Box 1)
    - Tectonic Geography of Southwestern New England and Southeastern New York. (Box 1)
  - 1904
    - The Tectonic Geography of Eastern Asia. (Box 1)
  - 1905
    - The Configuration of the Rock Floor of Greater New York. (Box 1)
    - The Grand Eruption of Vesuvius in 1906. (Box 1)
    - Origin of the Channels Surrounding Manhattan Island, New York. (Box 1)
  - 1906
    - America and Seismological Research. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence Relating to a Study of an Area of Crystalline Rocks in Southwestern New England. (Box 1)
    - Gaudix formation of Granada, Spain. (Box 1)
  - 1907
    - The Charleston Earthquake of 1886 in a New Light. (Box 1)
    - Editorial. Reprinted from the (Journal of Geology), February March, 1907. (Box 1)
    - The Goldschmidt Law of Complication Applied to the Solar System. (Box 1)
    - The Iron Ores of the Salisbury District of Connecticut, New York, and Massachusetts. (Box 1)
    - Memorial Address: Nathaniel Southgate Shaler. (Box 1)
    - Origin of Ocean Basins in the Light of the New Seismology. (Box 1)
    - The Pre-Cambrian Volcanic and Intrusive Rocks of the Fox River Valley Wisconsin. (Box 1)
    - Seismotectonic Lines and Lineaments (Box 1)
    - A Rejoinder. (Box 1)
    - Some Topographic Features Formed at the Time of Earthquakes and the Origin of Mounds in the Gulf Plain. (Box 1)
    - Studies for students: the recent advance in seismology. (Box 1)
    - Der Ursprung der Ozeanbecken im Lichte der modernen Seismologie. (Box 1)
  - 1908
    - Apparatus for instruction in geography and structural geology. (Box 1)
    - A Study of the Damage to Bridges During Earthquakes. (Box 1)
  - 1909
    - The Evolution and the Outlook of Seismic Geology. (Box 1)
    - The Latest Calabrian Disaster. (Box 1)
    - The Messina Earthquake. (Box 1)
    - New laboratory methods for instruction in geography. (Box 1)
    - Research and the Graduate School. (Box 1)
  - 1910
    - An American Laboratory for Earthquake Investigation. (Box 1)
    - Characteristics of the Inland (Box 1)
    - Ice of the Arctic Regions. (Box 1)
    - The Cycle of Mountain Glaciation. (Box 1)
    - The Earthquake of 1872 in the Owens Valley, California. (Box 1)
    - Earthquakes, An Introduction to Seismic Geology. (Box 1)
    - The Ice Masses on and About the Antarctic Continent. (Box 1)
    - Proposition de M. Wm. H. Hobbs Relative a une cooperation internationale pour l 'e' tude des fractures de l 'e'corce terrestre. (Box 1)
    - Reviews.
      - "Los temblores de Zanatepec, Oaxaca, a fines de septiembre de 1902," E. Bose. (Box 1)
      - "A Villafana y Garcia y Garcia, El temblor del 14 de abril de 1907," E. Boso. (Box 1)
      - "Catalogo de los temblores (macroseismos) sentidos en la Republica Mexicana durante los anos 1904 a 1908," Jose G. Aguilera. (Box 1)
  - 1911
    - The Pleistocene Glaciation of North American Viewed in the Light of Our Knowledge of Existing Continental Glaciers. (Box 1)
    - Repeating Patterns in the Relief and in the Structure of the Land. (Box 1)
    - Requisite Conditions for the Formation of Ice Ramparts. (Box 1)
  - 1913
    - Variations in Composition of Pelitic Sediments in Relation to Magmatic Differentation. (Box 1)
  - 1914
    - Eduard Seuss. (Box 1)
    - Mechanics of Arcuate Mountains. (Box 1)
  - 1915
    - Improvements in Methods of Study of Structural Geology. (Box 1)
    - The Role of the Glacial Anticyclone in the Air Circulation of the Globe. (Box 1)
  - 1916
    - Assumptions Involved in the Doctrine of Isostatic Compensation, with a Note on Hecker's Determination of Gravity at Sea. (Box 1)
    - The Ferrel Doctrine of Polar Calms and its Disproof in Recent Observations. (Box 1)
  - 1917
    - Address of the President of the Michigan Academy of Science. (Box 1)
    - The Outlook for Democracy. (Box 1)
    - A Pilgrimage in Northeastern Africa, with Studies of Desert Conditions. (Box 1)
  - 1918
    - The Achilles Heel of the German Monster. (Box 1)
    - A Correspondence with the University of Wisconsin. (Box 1)
    - The Crack in Germany's Armor. (Box 1)
    - The Erosional and Degradational Process of Deserts, with Especial Reference to the Origin of Desert Depressions. (Box 1)
    - The Peculiar Weathering Processes of Desert Regions with Illustrations from Egypt and the Soudan. (Box 1)
    - A Pioneer Movement for Americanization. (Box 1)
    - The World War and its Consequences. (Box 1)
  - 1919
    - The Conspiracy Against the Independence of the American Republic. (Box 1)
    - Reviews, La Face de la terre, par E. Seuss. (Box 1)
  - 1920
    - The Mechanics of the Glacial Anticyclone Illustrated by Experiment. (Box 1)
    - Popular Government and the Nominating Convention. (Box 1)
    - Would President Wilson's Covenant of the League of Nations Prevent War? (Box 1)
  - 1921
    - The Fixed Glacial Anticyclone Compared to the Migrating Anticyclone. (Box 1)
    - History Teaching and American Citizenship. (Box 1)
    - Memoir of Robert Edwin Peary. (Box 1)
    - Post-Glacial Faulting in the French River District of Ontario. (Box 1)
    - The Southwestern Michigan Meteor of November 26, 1919. (Box 1)
    - Studies of the Cycle of Glaciation. (Box 1)
  - 1922
    - Les Glaciers du Monde Actuel. (Box 1)
    - Les Guirlandes Insularies et la Formation des Montognes. (Box 1)
    - The So-called [horst] of the Harz Mountains and its Enveloping Permian and Mesozoic Formations. (Box 1)
  - 1923
    - The Asiatic Arcs. (Box 1)
    - The new Steel Industry of Australia: How it will Effect America's Exports to that Country. (Box 1)
    - The Rate of Movement in Vertical Earth Adjustments Connected with the Growth of Mountains. (Box 1)
    - Sounding the Depths of the Ocean: Recently Invented Sea-Sounding Instruments Which Mark a New Epoch in Safeguarding Ships at Sea. (Box 1)
    - The Trough-Deeps of the Island Arcs. (Box 1)
  - 1924
    - De Montessus de Ballore. (Box 1)
  - 1925
    - The Cause of Earthquakes: Especially Those of the Eastern United States. (Box 1)
    - Meteorologie: L'asmetrie de la circulation atmospherique. (Box 1)
    - The Source of the Cold Air of the North "Polar Front." (Box 1)
    - The Unstable Middle Section of the Island Arcs. (Box 1)
  - 1926
    - The First Greenland Expedition of the University. (The [Michigan Alumnus]) (Box 1)
    - Petrography of an Area of the Western Pacific. (Box 1)
    - Radio Talks on Science. (Box 1)
  - 1927
    - An Explorer's Experience with the Greenland Glacial Anticyclone. (Box 1)
    - The First Greenland Expedition of the University of Michigan. (Reprint, [The Geographical Review].) (Box 1)
  - 1928
    - Some curious early accounts of the Greenland Foehn. (Box 1)
  - 1929
    - Aerological Results of the Greenland Expeditions of the University of Michigan. (Box 1)
    - An Arctic Airplane Route Between America and Europe. (Box 1)
    - Climatic zones and Periods of Glaciation. (Box 1)
    - Engineering and Polar Exploration. (Box 1)
    - The Greenland Flying Route to Europe. (Box 1)
    - Navy Day at the University of Michigan a Huge Success: Many of Theodore Roosevelt's Policies given in Support of an Adequate National Defense for the United States. (Box 1)
  - 1930
    - Coordinated Aerological Studies in Greenland. (Box 1)
    - Stress Conditions Within the Lithosphere as Revealed by Earthquakes. (Box 1)
  - 1931
    - Investigations in Aerological and Other Research in Greenland. (Box 1)
    - Loess, Pebble Bands, and Boulders from Glacial Outwash of the Greenland Continental Glacier. (Box 1)
    - The Origin of the Loess Associated with Continental Glaciation Based Upon Studies in Greenland. (Box 1)
  - 1932
    - Polar Regions. (Box 1)
    - Wilkes Land Rediscovered. (Box 1)
  - 1933
    - The Eastern Landfalls of Wilkes Within the Australian Sector of the Antarctic. (Box 1)
    - The Glacial Anticyclones. (Box 1)
    - Visibility and the Discovery of Polar Lands. (Box 1)
  - 1934
    - Discovery of a New Sketch of Cape Hudson in the Antarctic. (Box 1)
    - Evolution in the Travel Technique of Polar Exploration. (Box 1)
    - The Glaciers of Mountain and Continent. (Box 1)
    - John Wesley Powell. (Box 1)
    - Memorial of Charles Wilford Cook. (Box 1)
  - 1935
    - A Call for Information Concerning Etched Erratic Boulders. (Box 1)
    - Admiral Peary, the Discoverer of the North Pole. (Box 1)
    - A Footnote to University History. (Box 1)
    - The Glacial Anticyclones. (Box 1)
    - The Glaciers of Mountain and Continent. (Box 1)
    - The Origin of the Loess Associated with Continental Glaciation Based Upon Studies in Greenland. (Box 1)
    - Peary's Discovery of the North Pole. (Box 1)
  - 1936
    - Reviews. "The Fiord Region of East Greenland," Louise A. Boyd. (Box 1)
  - 1937
    - A Biography of Peary. (Box 1)
    - Conditions of Exceptional Visibility Within High Latitudes, Particularly as a Result of Superior Mirage. (Box 1)
    - Discovery and Exploration Within the Area to the West of the Kane Basin. (Box 1)
    - Literature and Especially Poetry on Polar Expeditions. (Box 1)
    - Peary (Box 1)
    - The Engineer. (Box 1)
    - Peary's Journey to the Pole. (Box 1)
    - The Progress of Discovery and Exploration Within the Arctic Region. (Box 1)
  - 1938
    - The Snow of Outstanding Mountain Peaks. (Box 1)
  - 1939
    - America in the Antarctic. (Box 1)
    - Antarctic Names. (Box 1)
    - The Discoveries of Antarctica Within the American Sector, as Revealed by Maps and Documents. (Box 1)
    - The Discovery of Antarctica: A Reply to Professor R. N. Rudmose Brown. (Box 1)
    - Geographical Review. Letter to Dr. E. G. Conklin, v. p. and Executive officer, American Philosophical Society, Regarding an Unfavorable Review by Arthur R. Hinks of Hobb's Article "The Discoveries of Antarctica Within the American Sector as Revealed by Maps and Documents." (Box 1)
    - The Pack Ice of the Weddell Sea. (Box 1)
    - A Remarkable Example of Polar Mirage. (Box 1)
  - 1940
    - American Antarctic Discoveries. (Box 1)
    - Centenary Celebration of the Wilkes Exploring Expedition. (Box 1)
    - Conditions at the Front of a Retreating Ice Sheet. (Box 1)
    - The Discovery of Wilkes Land. (Box 1)
  - 1941
    - The Defense of Greenland. (Box 1)
    - The Department of Geology. (Box 1)
    - Early Maps of Antarctic Land, True and False. (Box 1)
  - 1942
    - Caribou and the Meat Shortage. (Box 1)
    - Latin America and Hemisphere Defense. (Box 1)
  - 1943
    - American Antarctic Discoveries, 1819-1940. (Box 1)
    - Discovery in Eastern Washington of a New Lobe of the Pleistocene Continental Glacier. (Box 1)
    - The Glacial Anticyclone and the European Continental Glacier. (Box 1)
    - The Glacial Anticyclone and the Continental Glaciers of North America. (Box 1)
    - The Growth of an Ice Sheet. (Box 1)
    - In the Mandated Pacific Islands. (Box 1)
    - Reports from Recipients of Grants from the Research Funds. (Box 1)
    - Wind and Soil. (Box 1)
  - 1944
    - Mountain Growth, A Study of the Southwestern Pacific Region. (Box 1)
    - New Volcanoes and a New Mountain Range. (Box 1)
    - Nourishment of the Greenland Continental Glacier. (Box 1)
    - The Pacific Island Fortress. (Box 1)
  - 1945
    - The Origin of Gumbotils of the Upper Mississippi Valley. (Box 1)
  - 1947
    - Review. "The Voyage of Captain Bellinghausen to the Antarctic Seas." (Box 1)
  - 1948
    - The Climate of the Arctic as Viewed by the Explorer and Meteorologist. (Box 1)
    - A Proposed Sea-level Ship Canal Across the Isthmus of Tehauntepec. (Box 1)
    - Tehauntepec Canal Proposal. (Box 1)
  - 1949
    - Crustal Movement in the Great Lakes Area: A Discussion. (Box 1)
  - 1950
    - Palmer's Map of the South Shetlands and the Palmer Peninsula. (Box 1)
    - The Pleistocene History of the Mississippi River. (Box 1)
    - The Problem of a New Trans-isthmian Canal. (Box 1)
    - The Track of the Columbus Caravels in 1492. (Box 1)
    - Verrazano's Voyage Along the North American Coast in 1524. (Box 1)
  - 1951
    - The Fourteenth-Century Discovery of America by Antonio Zeno. (Box 1)
  - Undated
    - The American Ancestry and the Descendants of William Herbert and Sara Kimball Hobbs. (Box 1)
    - Michigan Earthquakes and Their Glacial Cause. (Box 1)
    - Publications of William Herbert Hobbs, 1886-1926. (Box 1)
    - The World War and Its Consequences: Bibliography for a Six Weeks Course of Study. (Box 1)